"Efficacy and Safety of Fillers, Chemical Peels,
and Laser Skin Resurfacing"
The third most common
cosmetic procedures in the US,
each done nearly
a million times a year,
are chemical peels
and laser skin "resurfacings,"
to create a "controlled
injury to the face."
The reasoning is that
the regeneration, repair,
and remodeling of the damage
can result in a more
tightened appearance,
but may or may not
actually help with wrinkles.
The inflammation caused by these
types of facials causes edema,
fluid retention, in the face
that, because of the swelling,
can cause
a transient improvement
in the appearance
of fine wrinkles,
but in the end may do
more harm than good.
Short-term side-effects include
bruising, swelling, itching,
crusting, redness,
infection, acne, and milia,
which are little white cysts.
Long-lasting side-effects can
include persistent redness,
pigmentation changes,
and scarring.
The second most common cosmetic
procedure, after Botox,
is volumizing injections
of soft tissue fillers,
carried out about 3 million
times a year in the US alone.
Studies show subjective patient
satisfaction is often high,
though long-term efficacy data
are lacking
because people tend to undergo
subsequent procedures.
Adverse outcomes occur
in about 1 in 40 procedures,
most commonly bruising,
discoloration,
or unsightly lumps and bumps.
Lumps are the most frequently
reported adverse event
reported to the FDA,
followed by infection.
It's important
to not apply makeup
or otherwise touch
the injection sites
for at least four hours
to prevent introducing bacteria
into the needle tracks.
The most devastating
filler complication
is permanent blindness
due to an accidental
injection into an artery,
which can cause skin necrosis
but most seriously
can cause an embolus
that lodges into
the ophthalmic artery
and cuts off blood flow
to your retina.
This is exceedingly rare,
on the order of
1 in 1,000 nose injections,
for example,
and in nearly all the cases.
the vision loss
was only in one eye.
There are some factors that
mediate the blindness risk.
Autologous fat injections--
when they inject your own
liposuctioned fat--
seem to be the riskiest,
since they use a larger
volume and needle,
though other facial injections,
including platelet-rich plasma,
have also resulted in
irreversible vision loss.
To prevent this, medical
personnel are always taught
to aspirate a bit first,
pull back the plunger
on the syringe
to look for
that red flash of blood
that would indicate
you're in an artery.
Unfortunately this can give
a false sense of security,
as tiny movements of the needle
can change its position.
The highest risk area is
the glabellar region,
the skin between the eyebrows
and over the nose.
Unfortunately there does not
appear to be a safe zone,
since there's
a rich web of connections
among arteries
throughout the face.
Though blindness
from filler injections
has been said to occur
in any location on the face,
there do not appear
to be any cases
arising solely
from lip augmentation.
Like with Botox, these days,
a large fraction
of filler injections
are done by non-healthcare
professionals
in a medical spa-type setting.
This raises concerns
about illegal
(non-FDA approved) fillers.
There are reports of injections
with everything
from rubber cement
to Fix-a-Flat,
resulting in
disfigurement and even death.